Guide to the Scandinavian Fraternity Of America. District Lodge No. 7 records 1900-1990
Montana Historical Society
1900-1990
Montana Historical Society Archives
MC 278
Scandinavian Fraternity of America. District Lodge No. 7
2 linear feet of shelf space
Records of the Scandinavian Fraternity of America District Lodge No. 7 (Pacific Northwest) consists of a minute book (1900-1932) for the Grand Lodge of the Scandinavian Brotherhood and its successor District 7 of the Scandinavian Fraternity of America; and a minute book (1941-1945) of District 7. There are subgroups for the Helena chapter No. 253, including correspondence, minor financial records, and membership applications; and for the Kalispell chapter No.233, including financial records, minutes, and membership materials.
Historical Note:
The Scandinavian Fraternity of America was founded in 1915, as a consolidation of three other organizations, including the Scandinavian Brotherhood. The first convention was held that year in Chicago, Illinois. Like many similar ethnic organizations of the early 1900s, the Scandinavian Fraternity was principally a beneficial group to aid its membership when threatened by sickness, unemployment, or death. It also had a separate category of social members. The organization was open to both women and men, and to their non-Scandinavian spouses. The national organization declined in membership during the 1970s and 1980s.
Capital City Lodge No. 253 of the Scandinavian Fraternity of America was founded in Helena about 1926. It continued to operate until about 1977. The Kalispell Lodge No. 233 (originally the Three Leaf Clover Lodge No. 233) was founded in November 1924. It continued in existence until sometime after 1990.
Records of the Scandinavian Fraternity of America District Lodge No. 7 (Pacific Northwest) consists of a minute book (1900-1932) for the Grand Lodge of the Scandinavian Brotherhood and its successor District 7 of the Scandinavian Fraternity of America; and a minute book (1941-1945) of District 7. The Capital City Lodge No. 253 subgroup includes correspondence (1944-1950) mainly with the Supreme Lodge (national organization), District Lodge No. 7 (regional organization for the Pacific Northwest), Butte Lodge No. 1, and members of the Capital City Lodge; minor financial records (1948-1950); and membership applications (1926-1977). The Kalispell Lodge No.233 subgroup includes a cash book (1928-1947); a journal (1957-1976) of receipts, expenditures, and deposits; membership materials (1924-1970); and minutes (1925-1990).
Arranged by subgroup and series
Collection open for research.
Acquisition information available upon request
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Scandinavian Fraternity of America. District Lodge No. 7
Fraternal organizations --Montana; Scandinavian Americans--Montana
Montana; Scandinavian Americans
Detailed Description of the Collection
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection
- Supreme Lodge
  - Historical Materials
    - Notes on history of national Supreme Lodge (copies from website of Balch Institute for Ethnic Studies; and from reports by H. A. Fisher and by Thelma Schuessler); Index of members, 1963-1993, undated (Box-folder 1 / 1)
  - Organizational Records
    - Constitution and bylaws, revised, 1983 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
- District 7 (Pacific Northwest)
  - Organizational Records
    - Board minutes (including convention proceedings, financial reports, and committee reports: 1900-1915 is Scandinavian Brotherhood of America; in 1916 it became District 7 of Scandinavian Fraternity of America, 1900-1932 (Volume 1)
    - Board minutes (including convention proceedings, financial reports, and committee reports), 1941-1945 (Volume 2)
    - Constitution and bylaws, revised, 1983 (Box-folder 1 / 3)
    - Delegate list, visitors, membership, circa 1967 (Box-folder 1 / 4)
- Capital City Lodge No. 253 (Helena, Mont.)
  - General Correspondence
    - Letters from the Supreme Lodge, the District Lodge, Butte Lodge No. 1 (mostly regarding tri-city meetings with Butte and Anaconda), a letter dated May 19, 1948, listing deceased members, and thank-you's from members, 1944-1948 (Box-folder 1 / 5)
    - Letters from the Supreme Lodge, the District Lodge, Butte Lodge No. 1 (mostly regarding the joint picnic), a letter from J. Palmer and Dorothy Lalum withdrawing their memberships, a letter dated April 27, 1950, containing a list of new members in 1950 and when they were initiated, and thank-you's from members, 1949-1950 (Box-folder 1 / 6)
    - Letters from Butte Lodge No. 1, a letter from Marian H. Lindstrom withdrawing her membership, and thank-you's from members, undated (Box-folder 1 / 7)
  - Financial Records
    - Bills and receipts, 1948-1950, undated (Box-folder 1 / 8)
  - Organizational Records
    - Applications for membership: A-N, 1926-1977 (Box-folder 1 / 9-22)
    - Applications for membership: O-W, 1926-1976 (Box-folder 2 / 1-7)
    - Resolutions of respect and sympathy / tributes, 1928-1968 (Box-folder 2 / 8)
    - Committee reports on annual fall picnics, 1947, 1949; inter-city bowling results with the Butte Lodge, 1950; nominations for officers, 1950; Alice Fredericks' report on the national convention, 1950; order of memorial services, undated; list of committees, undated), 1947-1950 (Box-folder 2 / 7)
- Kalispell Lodge No. 233
  - Financial Records
    - Cash book (also includes semi-annual report of receipts and disbursements), 1928-1947 (Box-folder 3 / 1)
    - Journal of receipts, deposits, and expenditures, 1957-1976 (Box-folder 3 / 2)
  - Organizational Records
    - Bylaws, revised, 1990 (Box-folder 3 / 3)
    - Charter members list, 1924 (Box-folder 3 / 4)
    - Membership list, 1930-1935 (Box-folder 3 / 5)
    - Membership register, 1946-1960, 1970 (Box-folder 3 / 6)
    - Minute books, 1925-1944 (Box-folder 3 / 7-10)
    - Minute books, 1945-1977 (Box-folder 4 / 1-8)
    - Minute books, 1978-1990 (Box-folder 5 / 1-2)
    - Officers roll books (includes lists of members eligible to serve as delegates to District Lodge 7), 1924-1990 (Box-folder 5 / 3-4)